[Music]
Welcome to the busy central launch
edition 2025 release wave 2.
I will try to explain one new big
feature in sustainability about CSRD
reporting. We call this session CSRD
reporting but this is not only for CSRD.
You will see some other compliance
reporting will be covered but we use
CSRD as the most hot topics in European
Union. My name is Alexander Toto as a
product manager for this area. So before
we explain in details what is about and
show you demo uh first about business
values
uh what is the most important the most
important is to provide a regulatory
compliance. So for all companies who are
supposed to report CSRD or other ESG uh
standards, you can see here CSRD, SRS,
BR, SR, so many different standards.
With this functionality, now you will be
a regulatory compliance. And the other
side, it will streamline data handling.
So you will definitely eliminate complex
uh repetitive uh prone uh errorrone data
entries copying from one table from one
solution to another. So it will
definitely improve accuracy efficiency
so you can easily use the boat from both
worlds and when it's about both worlds
how you will report I said both worlds
we have one side busy central and the
other side we have external ESG
reporting so we are using business
central for entering all sustainability
information we have our sustainability
ledger entry but this reporting is not
only about sustainability information
not only environmental so There are ES
this is ESG so we have social guarance
so you can use information from
employees from statistical accounts from
different sources financials and so on
but all our entries are in a busy
central so we will start from there and
transfer into external ESG reporting
tool and report from there but before we
start to calculate all of this we can
collect all standard forg reporting tool
so this is why we have birectional
communication between these two tools
to install external ESG reporting you
can use this link. So you can find link
how to install actually this is not link
for installing this is link with the
documentation how to install this is
power app so you can install relatively
easy and what is important uh when you
uh install you must have power app
license uh for this uh tool. So uh you
do not need to pay anything additional.
So this is free of charge but you must
have power license minimum one power lab
license to work with this functionality.
Once you have it what is included in
this tool? So we have different
standards included. So you will have
CSRD uh reporting for European Union. So
Australian uh reporting standard then
you will have Indian uh reporting
standards uh GRIS. So you have different
standards. Of course these standards are
subject of changes but what is good
using the same model you can easily
build your own templates. You can copy
one of them uh remove what you need
change relatively easy. So this is full
tool for all types of ESG reportings and
you can create uh special format you
need.
So
on the other side we need to have place
where we will calculate all information
we have in the business central. So now
we have ESG aggregation reporting
aggregation page and this is actually
not page this is uh not only page this
is tool this whole tool for calculating.
So this is central place in the business
central for all these calculations and
now I want to emphasize we are using
this for ESG reporting but you can use
this for any table you will see you can
connect to any tables and you can use
for making maybe some additional
reportings as well. So you can group you
can map with different data sources you
can use formula. So this is combination
of few different tools in a business
central
about setup what you need to do before
you start with reporting. First you need
to connect with a data versse. So you
will use data connection setup regular
you can use wizard. So first establish
connection between busy central and your
data environment once when you deploy
power app there because this power app
will be based on a data. Then in a
business central you need to enable data
synchronization. This is mandatory.
And then in a sustainability setup you
need to enable data integration. So this
is important. Uh this enabling data
integration is connected with data
integration of sustainability
information. So you can see on this page
on this slide so many different tables
are synchronized. So once when you
enable data integration in
sustainability setup all of them will be
connected and mapped. So this is not
easy for connection. You can change it.
But if you want to use for this type of
re reporting, you do not you're not
supposed to do it. And please be careful
with that. You you really need to
understand what you're doing. And to uh
reporting number of serious. So you need
to have uh ESG standard reporting number
of serious. These standards related with
CSRD FRS uh and so on different
standards. So you need to have uh number
of serious in the business central and
you need to have reporting number of
serious once when you collect reporting
and when you post it. So this is
prerequisite to start with the uh usage
of this functionality and then how
process is working not so simple process
because we have two tools different
things are uh has to be done in
different places. So we will start with
the external ESG reporting. You first
need to go there and to create
assessment and based on assessment you
will get assessment requirements.
Assessment will be automatically
integrated with a business central to
ESG reporting name and assessment
requirement into ESG reporting lines.
This is uh these two uh tables are about
uh aggregation tool in business central
you just saw. Then we will choose the
right ESG reporting name. Once when you
have you need to choose which name you
want to use and then map ESG reporting
lines with the specific data sources you
need to find for example sustainability
ledger entry for specific line and find
specific value you want to collect from
there. When you finish everything you
have option to preview your results to
just to be sure everything is okay. If
everything is okay you can run calculate
and post ESG report. When you do it,
system will automatically populate facts
inside the external EG reporting tool.
So you will be ready for reporting.
But probably you need manually to update
some missing facts. Why I say that?
Because there are many different facts
for example risk assessments and you
need to do it manually because there are
pure textile information. So you need to
do it manually and then when you finish
you need to export into CSRD format. So
let's switch to the demo.
As I said first we will start with a
power app. Actually this is this power
app is uh ESG external ESG reporting and
you need to find assessments on the on
the left side. Once when you find the
assessments you can press nine. Okay,
you can see I have already a lot of
active assessments. But when you want to
create, you want to create click uh new
to create new assessment and then you
can choose different standards how you
want to set up. I will choose for
example CSRD and this is subject of this
topic but as I said there are different
standards and you can use any of them.
When you choose standard you will choose
a period you want to report. So there is
additional table you can set up that
this is from the beginning of year until
the end of year or whatever you want to
report and more or less that's it. This
is what you need to configure. This is
enough for reporting.
Okay. You can enter uh additional
organization unit and so on if you're a
bigger company but other information are
not necessary for integration. So once
you have it you will click save and
that's it.
But next step if you remember I
mentioned once when you create
assessment we need to have requirements.
So we need to choose requirements tab
and you will see so fast but in general
in practice you will wait two three
minutes so all requirements will be
configured based on a standard you use
in our case CSRD standard. So it will
take few minutes time because there are
hundreds of different lines there. But
once this is finished that's it we
completed this first step in a data
versse tool. So ESG external ESG
reporting that's it. Now we will switch
to the business central
and switching to B central. We will
start with ESG reporting aggregation
tool.
As I said we have names. So we need to
choose the right name. So this is ESG
reporting name. We will choose CSRD ble
I use for this case. And then we will
find all lines we have created based on
requirements. So all these lines are
copied for requirements.
Now you need to know you need to
understand ESG reporting. So you need to
know all these um codes where you need
to report what you need to report
because the most of them will not be
used from the business central. In the
business central you can find as I said
environmental you can find about
employees some statistical accounts
financial accounts but not for all of
them. Some of them will be actually many
of them will be populated in um uh data
versse toolback. So once when you find
and you locate one you want to configure
with the carbon equivalent information.
Okay. You need to go into table number
find sustainability ledger entry table
and that's it. Okay. And next we need to
find fields we want to use because we
can summarize different fields. Now for
this um line we need to calculate carbon
equivalent. So I will choose carbon
equivalent line
cared field actually and confirm. And
next step will be to use type uh of uh
handling with this information. So we
can summarize or count. For example for
employees maybe some other reasons we
need to count uh some options but here
we just need to summarize. So we will
choose summarize and then we need to set
up a filter. There is a filter because
in this case we need to separate
different uh lines per different um
scopes for scope one, scope two, scope
three. So now we can set up filter for
count from uh scope one. Then another
line for scope two, another line for
scope three. So all of them are using
the same table number, the same field
number but different filters. Okay. Once
when we complete it, we will get filter
already inside. We need to enter
reporting unit of measure and eventually
you can use row type but in general this
is net change. Additionally we can use
for all of these lines because some of
line you can create manually if you need
to recalculate something because maybe
some information is not uh available as
a uh as a row information on B central.
So you need to calculate them. So you
can easily create new line and you will
not show this line. You can choose not
to be showed in reporting. You can
change a sign because if this is uh
filled for example with negative sign
and you need to use positive you can
just change the sign you want to use and
then you can use um different uh model
of um rounding without rounding on to or
to round one all of them.
So if I choose for example to one and I
can switch to another table I can make
uh additional setup. So again
I will create table
and now I can choose a formula because
of some of them I will use the table but
for some of them I will use formula.
Once I create a formula I can populate.
This is the same model formulas we are
using in financial reporting. So we can
use all operators multiply dividing plus
minus. So you can use all of them. You
can use brackets, you can use anything
from mathematical purpose you can use.
So if you need to calculate percentage,
you have here as a unit of measure is
percentage and I need just to calculate
what is a percentage of one scope into
completely uh emissions. So this is easy
to be configured. Eventually I can add
for example another table for employees
and then I can choose
uh counting because as I said I want to
count employees. I do not want to
summarize them and more or less that's
it. We can use all of them but what I
want to emphasize if you do not have
power apply and if you do not want to
use ESG external tool you can still use
this functionality you can create lines
in ESG aggregation tool manually and
collect them all of them and you can
prepare everything what you have in a
business central and then manually
populate CSRD or some other reporting
tool. So this is still possible. You are
not uh enforced to use this integration.
So this integration will help you if you
want to collect all standards to have
everything smooth. But if you want just
to prepare this information, you can
easily do it without integration.
So now you can click preview to see what
is inside. As I have just a few lines, I
can say yes, this is what I configured.
So all good. I can even go deeper. I can
uh look up what is inside. So I can see
all information are as I supposed to
have. So if everything is okay, I can go
back.
So everything is okay. I will go uh I
will close this preview page. I do not
need it. And I would like now to
calculate and to post ESG reporting. I
just need to click here calculate and
post. Of course, I will be asked if I
want if I'm sure. Yes, I am sure. And
then everything is posted. So all good.
What I need to do I need to switch to
posted ESG reports. So I will find the
name because I use the batch name. So by
this batch name you will be you will
find the posted document. And this is
what I said even if you do not have
integration you can go there and you can
find reports you we even have CSRD
preparation reports. So you can collect
and print all important fields you
wanted to report even without
integration. But in this case we are
using full integration. So everything is
there everything what we populated is
already inside the business central. So
that's it we finish with the business
central and I said once we do it in the
business central in a background stis
will uh copy all our values we have here
into facts to the extent ESG reporting.
So we will switch back to ESG reporting
and we will find our assessment we use
CSRDBLE
and now we just need to find a proper uh
code and then we will find one we used
and then when you expand you will find
fact information. So now we have fact
value,90
with the unit of kilogram. So everything
was copied from B central. So this is
about everything what is posted there in
a busy center will be copied as effects
in an appropriate place uh based on a
standard we used in assessments. So now
we can go back to general and export
reporting.
So for exporting you need to export to
ex uh to excel. We will provide
documentation proper links to ESG
external ESG reporting tool. how to
convert from Excel to XBRL for reporting
but primarily it will be exported to
Excel.
So I hope so this is not so complicated.
I know this is complex topic especially
compliance with integration but I hope
so it was not so complicated so you can
understand how it works. It is important
to remember you can use this with a full
integration but you can use in a busy
central even without integration to
prepare only preparation document for
manually populating CSRD or other
standards.
Before we close this session I would
like to remind you we have good links
where you can find a lot of interesting
information about Business Central. Then
do not forget if you are not already
subscribed to our LinkedIn channel. You
can find all weekly and uh news
announcements and so on
and watch YouTube for more videos about
Business Central aka MSBC YouTube. You
can find this and other videos about
sustainability. In this series, we will
have a lot of videos about
sustainability. Many new functionalities
are prepared for this release and not
only about sustainability about other
functionalities in this edition and
previous editions.
So, thank you for watching this video.